This video is sponsored by the
all-in-one website builder and business
management software, ODO. Use my link in
the description to get started for free.
An ancient memorization technique known
as the method of Losi or the memory
palace has been shown to meaningfully
increase a person's ability to recall
information with some studies finding
that an individual's recall improves
upwards of 20% months after having
initially used the technique. Though
this is undoubtedly profound, perhaps
what's even more fascinating is what the
technique reveals about how the mind
creates and [music] interprets meaning.
The very nature and modes in which we
think and can think better. The method
of losi works as follows. [music] First,
take the information you want to
remember. Then consider a familiar space
or route like an apartment, [music]
house, office, driving direction, or
walking path. Then visualize the
information in various physical
locations within that familiar space or
route. For example, if you wanted to
remember key talking points for a
speech, presentation, or important
[music] conversation, you could map out
a normal morning routine in your
apartment going from your bedroom to the
bathroom to the kitchen to the living
room to the front door to the driveway
and so on. At each of these locations,
you would then imagine one of the
talking points or ideas in the
appropriate order of the presentation.
ideally imagining it in some absurd or
humorous form or spot. Then when you
need to recall the whole list of talking
points, you would simply mentally walk
the same normal routine through your
apartment and retrieve each talking
point. The reason this method works is
because it utilizes and reinforces what
our brains are already good at, forming
connections between pieces of
information and visual, spatial,
emotional, or symbolic contexts and
[music] cues. Though this is why the
method works, one is still left to
wonder why our brains benefit from this
process. [music] How does our brain even
create these visual and spatial cues
inside our mind? Furthermore, why are
some thoughts in the form of words, some
in visuals, and some in senses or
abstractions? Why are some people better
at remembering, some better at
communicating, and some better at
thinking in general? Can one improve the
way they think? All of these questions
[music] gesture at the same thing. the
strange, nebulous and diverse nature of
[music] thought.
There are roughly five primary modes in
which people experience [music]
thoughts. One is an internal voice, a
mental narration or internal monologue
where one is simultaneously the speaker
and listener inside their head. Another
is through visuals and images. Third is
through feelings, the pushes and pulls
of emotional states. Fourth is through
sensory awareness. And last is through
abstract [music] concepts and
intuitions.
Most people think using a combination of
a few if not all these various modes.
However, this is not the case for
everyone. Research suggests that a
majority of people report having a
primary mode, a dominant way in which
their thoughts are experienced and
directed. Some people think primarily
through an internal voice. Some people
think primarily through visuals, and
some people think primarily through
concepts or feelings with little to no
words or visuals. According to
psychologist Russell Herbert's research,
it is estimated that roughly 30 to 50%
of people regularly think through an
internal voice. Other research and
theories, including that of psychologist
Linda Silverman, suggest that roughly
30% of people regularly think through
visuals, [music]
with a smaller subset thinking primarily
or only through visuals. For individuals
like this latter subset, [music] there
is no primary mode of thinking blended
with secondary modes. Rather thought is
almost wholly experienced through a
single distinct mode. Often other modes
of thought are not even within the realm
of possibility. For example, roughly 4%
[music] of the global population is
estimated to have what is known as
aphantasia where they are entirely
incapable of clearly forming mental
images in their mind. For them, thoughts
are comprised solely of words, feelings,
or abstract concepts. On the other end
of the spectrum, [music] approximately 5
to 10% of the global population does not
have a strong inner voice or completely
lacks one altogether. For them, there is
no narrator or internal conversation.
Thoughts are comprised primarily of
images, [music] abstractions, or
feelings. If they want to think
something in words, they have to say it
out loud or write it down. In some
cases, visual thinkers have a condition
known as hyperfantasia, [music]
where they experience extremely vivid
mental scenes and objects that can
appear as real as external ones.
Regardless of whether we think more or
exclusively with visuals, [music]
words, or feelings, the thought that
other people can and do think
differently [music] from us, possibly in
a way that we can't even comprehend is
simultaneously all striking and somewhat
unsettling. [music] Individuals we talk
and interact with every day. Individuals
we love and feel we know [music] deeply
could and in some cases likely do think
in ways that are totally [music] foreign
to us. Animal scientist and author Dr.
Temple Grandon writes, "I think in
[music] pictures. Words are like a
second language to me. I translate both
spoken and written words into fullcolor
movies complete with sound which run
like a VCR tape in my head. When
somebody speaks to me, his words are
instantly translated into pictures.
Language-based thinkers often find this
phenomenon difficult to [music]
understand.
Confusion here is only natural. How
could anyone not think this [music] way
the way we do? To imagine how others
think in a way that we don't is
impossible. [music] It would require us
to think differently than we can, which
of course we cannot. We are all always
constrained [music] inside our head,
unable to escape the modes of our
thoughts and experiences, unable to
understand the world and others [music]
outside of it. In truth, we may all
think very similarly, but simply use
[music] different terms to describe the
same mental experiences. Alternatively,
we could all think very differently,
more than we are even aware of, but
[music] we simply use similar terms to
describe very different kinds of mental
experiences. Ultimately, all our mental
experiences [music]
are trapped by the guards of language.
They can never get past them. And so,
[music] neither can we, our unique sense
of self and the world. The fact that we
ever understand each other at all is a
wonder [music] that rivals thought
itself.
It is often said that the average person
has somewhere around 60,000 thoughts per
day. [music] The truth is simultaneously
simpler and more confounding. We don't
really know how many thoughts the
average person has per day. [music] That
isn't how thinking works. Thoughts
constantly flow, bubbling up in unique
forms for each of us and in each moment.
from short impulses to intense
ruminations, from visuals to words to
feelings. [music]
What is clear, however, is that we think
a lot and how we [music] think matters a
lot. How we think can affect tangible
things like what we are good at and
where we end up in life. For example,
people who think with vivid visuals are
more likely to remember precise details
from past events. They also tend to
pursue and succeed more in careers
[music] in art and media. Alternatively,
people with aphantasia or weaker visual
thinking tend to pursue and succeed more
in STEM fields. More than that, [music]
the quality of our experience in life is
of course also entwined with our
thoughts. Our experiences in life are
not [music] only unique based on our
modes of thought, but also the direction
we compel our thought, how we focus and
receive it. Psychologists Matthew
Killingsworth and Daniel Gilbert found
that 47% of our waking thoughts [music]
go to thinking about what isn't going on
around us. That means roughly half of
our existence is spent thinking about
what is not currently real. Instead,
[music] we are thinking about the past,
the future, or some totally imagined
reality. This isn't inherently bad.
[music] Mind wandering can lead to
powerful ideas and insights, can help us
overcome the past, and can protect us
from the future. [music] But thinking
about what is not is inherently a
deprivation of what is a sacrifice of
the present for some imagined
alternative reality. Killingsworth and
Gilbert Wright, the ability to think
about what is not happening is a
cognitive achievement that comes [music]
at an emotional cost. That cost they
found is greater unhappiness. Based on
their research, mind wandering explains
about 10.8% [music] of the variation in
people's momentto moment happiness.
While the activity that someone is doing
[music] only explains about 4.6%.
In other words, how we direct our
thoughts generally matters more than
what we are doing in any given moment.
In the words of psychologist and
philosopher William James, millions of
items of the outward order are present
to my senses which never properly enter
into my experience. Why? Because they
have no interest for me. My experience
is what I [music] agree to attend to.
Only those items which I notice shape my
mind. Without selective interest,
experience is an utter chaos. Interest
alone gives accent and emphasis, light
and shade, background and [music]
foreground intelligible perspective.
Somehow clumps of brain matter that
house neurons [music] that create
electrical impulses produce all of this.
The various modes of thinking and
perception, words, symbols, images,
sounds, feelings, and everything else.
It's easy to [music] forget this, to
just keep everything on the default mode
of perception and awareness and to
assume that every instance of subjective
experience [music]
is simple and straightforward and not
the miraculous profound display of
consciousness that it truly is. Perhaps
this [music] is what we need to remember
more than anything else. We should
strive to use the method of Losai to
create a memory palace of the entire
world, placing reminders for us at every
moment, place, [music] and opportunity
to remember the profoundity of
remembering itself. to see and recall
the immense and incomprehensible wonders
of [music] thought, of selfhood, of
consciousness, of existence. We live all
our lives in [music] our heads. We live
nearly half of it in imagined worlds. We
should decorate both with as much
beauty, humor, wonder, and presence
[music] as we can, however our thoughts
will allow.
If you enjoyed this video and you enjoy
my work, I'm happy to share that my new
book, The Terrible Paradox of
Self-awareness, is about to come out. It
explores many of these same ideas around
selfhood, consciousness, [music]
and how we can live well within the
absurd condition of our minds. It's
available for pre-order now through the
link in the description. And no matter
how we think, what we do with our
thoughts next matters a lot. how we
reflect them outwardly and express them
in the world. Whether it's through a
creative expression, a business, a
social cause, or all the above. This
video sponsor, ODU, provides the
platform, the canvas for you to [music]
do so at full scale. ODU makes building
a website not only easy and
comprehensive, but accessible with a
free website builder that lets you begin
without any friction. You start by
answering a few prompts, then you choose
the general look and feel you want, and
you already have a working first version
of your website. From there, you simply
tweak it, dragging and dropping dynamic
elements and features until you have
what you envisioned in your head. It's
an unrestrained way of letting your
thoughts and ideas [music] pour out and
become something tangible. Once you're
all set up and your site is live, ODU
also allows you to manage things like
inventory, accounting, project goals,
and more, all within the same integrated
platform. For example, if you're running
a small business, ODU can trigger
purchase orders, automate follow-ups,
schedule receipt confirmations, and keep
everything organized in one place. With
your first app free, unlimited hosting
and support, and a free custom domain
name for the first year, ODU ensures you
don't need to overthink anything. If you
want a simple, flexible way to build
something meaningful, you can get
started for free by using my link in the
description. And of course, as always,
thank you so much for watching in
general, and see you next video.